GREGORY JAMES SMITH

Instructor, Interdisciplinary Science and Research Program, John Overton High School

✓ gregory.smith2@mnps.org

\$ 570.762.2445

9 @paleodentist

RESUME SUMMARY

Motivated scientist with research experience in the academic sector tackling ambiguous research questions, developing code, and communicating scientific material to diverse audiences. I have a research background in geology and paleoecology and am currently leveraging my academic experience to teach interdisciplinary science and research concepts to students at John Overton High School in Nashville, TN. Recipient of over \$40,000 in grants focused on research, education, and outreach. Experience with designing engaging STEM curricula in both university and high school settings. Proficient with analytical programming languages including R, Python, and SQL.

WORK EXPERIENCE

Aug 2019 -	Instructor: Interdisciplinary Science and Research Program, John Overton High School
2018 - 2019	Graduate Teaching Fellow: Center for Teaching, Vanderbilt University
2013 - 2018	Graduate Research Assistant: Vanderbilt University and Penn State University
2012 - 2013	Environmental Scientist and Consultant: Earth Data Northeast, Inc., Exton, PA
EDUCATION	
EDUCATION Ph.D. (2019)	Vanderbilt University (VU): Earth and Environmental Sciences
	Vanderbilt University (VU): Earth and Environmental Sciences Penn State University (PSU): Geosciences

WRITTEN AND ORAL COMMUNICATION SKILLS

- Spoken Languages: English (native), Spanish (conversationally proficient)
- Funding Success: Recipient of over 22 grants and accolades totaling >\$40,000 in research and travel funds
- Technical Communication Experience: 7 scientific publications in peer-reviewed journals and 15 presentations at scientific society annual meetings over the last 8 years (ORCID: https://orcid.org/0000-0003-0060-2768/).
 My academic work has, for example, demonstrated dietary competition in the fossil record, named a new mastodon species, and used Monte Carlo analyses to test for extinction drivers over the last 70 million years.
- Nontechnical Communication Experience: Instructor for multiple courses in natural science, data science, and pedagogy at the K-12 and collegiate level; invited speaker at informal gatherings including Nashville Women's Breakfast Club and Adventure Science Center Adult Night

COMPUTATIONAL PROFICIENCY

- Programming Languages: SQL, R, Java, Python, Matlab, NetLogo, and Git
- Spatial and Image Processing Software: ArcGIS, FIJI, and Avizo 3D Studio
- Graphical and Organizational Software: Adobe Creative Cloud Products, Microsoft Office, and LateK

LEADERSHIP AND SERVICE ACTIVITIES

- Board of Directors, Friends of Fort Negley, Nashville, TN (2017 2023)
- Secretary, Vanderbilt Earth and Environmental Sciences Graduate Student Council (2017 2019)
- Facilitator, Penn State Earth and Mineral Science Exposition Open House (2010 2015)
- Vice President, Theta Chi Fraternity, Omega Chapter (2011)